2 Kings
Chapter 18:1-8

Hezekiah Becomes King of Judah

1 In the third year of the reign of Israel’s King Hoshea son of Elah, Ahaz’s son Hezekiah became king over Judah. 2 He was twenty-five years old when he began to reign, and he reigned twenty-nine years in Jerusalem. His mother was Abi, the daughter of Zechariah. 3 He did what the Lord approved, just as his ancestor David had done. 4 He eliminated the high places, smashed the sacred pillars to bits, and cut down the Asherah pole. He also demolished the bronze serpent that Moses had made, for up to that time the Israelites had been offering incense to it; it was called Nehushtan. 5 He trusted in the Lord God of Israel; in this regard there was none like him among the kings of Judah either before or after. 6 He was loyal to the Lord and did not abandon him. He obeyed the commandments that the Lord had given to Moses. 7 The Lord was with him; he succeeded in all his endeavors. He rebelled against the king of Assyria and refused to submit to him. 8 He defeated the Philistines as far as Gaza and its territory, from watchtower to fortified city.

John
Chapter 10:1-21

Jesus as the Good Shepherd

1 “I tell you the solemn truth, the one who does not enter the sheepfold by the door, but climbs in some other way, is a thief and a robber. 2 The one who enters by the door is the shepherd of the sheep. 3 The doorkeeper opens the door for him, and the sheep hear his voice. He calls his own sheep by name and leads them out. 4 When he has brought all his own sheep out, he goes ahead of them, and the sheep follow him because they recognize his voice. 5 They will never follow a stranger, but will run away from him, because they do not recognize the stranger’s voice.” 6 Jesus told them this parable, but they did not understand what he was saying to them.

7 So Jesus said again, “I tell you the solemn truth, I am the door for the sheep. 8 All who came before me were thieves and robbers, but the sheep did not listen to them. 9 I am the door. If anyone enters through me, he will be saved, and will come in and go out, and find pasture. 10 The thief comes only to steal and kill and destroy; I have come so that they may have life, and may have it abundantly.

11 “I am the good shepherd. The good shepherd lays down his life for the sheep. 12 The hired hand, who is not a shepherd and does not own sheep, sees the wolf coming and abandons the sheep and runs away. So the wolf attacks the sheep and scatters them. 13 Because he is a hired hand and is not concerned about the sheep, he runs away.

14 “I am the good shepherd. I know my own and my own know me— 15 just as the Father knows me and I know the Father—and I lay down my life for the sheep. 16 I have other sheep that do not come from this sheepfold. I must bring them too, and they will listen to my voice, so that there will be one flock and one shepherd. 17 This is why the Father loves me —because I lay down my life, so that I may take it back again. 18 No one takes it away from me, but I lay it down of my own free will. I have the authority to lay it down, and I have the authority to take it back again. This commandment I received from my Father.”

19 Another sharp division took place among the Jewish people because of these words. 20 Many of them were saying, “He is possessed by a demon and has lost his mind! Why do you listen to him?” 21 Others said, “These are not the words of someone possessed by a demon. A demon cannot cause the blind to see, can it?”

Luke
Chapter 9:28-62

The Transfiguration

28 Now about eight days after these sayings, Jesus took with him Peter, John, and James, and went up the mountain to pray. 29 As he was praying, the appearance of his face was transformed, and his clothes became very bright, a brilliant white. 30 Then two men, Moses and Elijah, began talking with him. 31 They appeared in glorious splendor and spoke about his departure that he was about to carry out at Jerusalem. 32 Now Peter and those with him were quite sleepy, but as they became fully awake, they saw his glory and the two men standing with him. 33 Then as the men were starting to leave, Peter said to Jesus, “Master, it is good for us to be here. Let us make three shelters, one for you and one for Moses and one for Elijah”—not knowing what he was saying. 34 As he was saying this, a cloud came and overshadowed them, and they were afraid as they entered the cloud. 35 Then a voice came from the cloud, saying, “This is my Son, my Chosen One. Listen to him!” 36 After the voice had spoken, Jesus was found alone. So they kept silent and told no one at that time anything of what they had seen.

Healing a Boy with an Unclean Spirit

37 Now on the next day, when they had come down from the mountain, a large crowd met him. 38 Then a man from the crowd cried out, “Teacher, I beg you to look at my son—he is my only child! 39 A spirit seizes him, and he suddenly screams; it throws him into convulsions and causes him to foam at the mouth. It hardly ever leaves him alone, torturing him severely. 40 I begged your disciples to cast it out, but they could not do so.” 41 Jesus answered, “You unbelieving and perverse generation! How much longer must I be with you and endure you? Bring your son here.” 42 As the boy was approaching, the demon threw him to the ground and shook him with convulsions. But Jesus rebuked the unclean spirit, healed the boy, and gave him back to his father. 43 Then they were all astonished at the mighty power of God.

Another Prediction of Jesus’ Suffering

But while the entire crowd was amazed at everything Jesus was doing, he said to his disciples, 44 “Take these words to heart, for the Son of Man is going to be betrayed into the hands of men.” 45 But they did not understand this statement; its meaning had been concealed from them, so that they could not grasp it. Yet they were afraid to ask him about this statement.

Concerning the Greatest

46 Now an argument started among the disciples as to which of them might be the greatest. 47 But when Jesus discerned their innermost thoughts, he took a child, had him stand by his side, 48 and said to them, “Whoever welcomes this child in my name welcomes me, and whoever welcomes me welcomes the one who sent me, for the one who is least among you all is the one who is great.”

On the Right Side

49 John answered, “Master, we saw someone casting out demons in your name, and we tried to stop him because he is not a disciple along with us.” 50 But Jesus said to him, “Do not stop him, for whoever is not against you is for you.”

Rejection in Samaria

51 Now when the days drew near for him to be taken up, Jesus set out resolutely to go to Jerusalem. 52 He sent messengers on ahead of him. As they went along, they entered a Samaritan village to make things ready in advance for him, 53 but the villagers refused to welcome him, because he was determined to go to Jerusalem. 54 Now when his disciples James and John saw this, they said, “Lord, do you want us to call fire to come down from heaven and consume them?” 55 But Jesus turned and rebuked them, 56 and they went on to another village.

Challenging Professed Followers

57 As they were walking along the road, someone said to him, “I will follow you wherever you go.” 58 Jesus said to him, “Foxes have dens and the birds in the sky have nests, but the Son of Man has no place to lay his head.” 59 Jesus said to another, “Follow me.” But he replied, “Lord, first let me go and bury my father.” 60 But Jesus said to him, “Let the dead bury their own dead, but as for you, go and proclaim the kingdom of God.” 61 Yet another said, “I will follow you, Lord, but first let me say goodbye to my family.” 62 Jesus said to him, “No one who puts his hand to the plow and looks back is fit for the kingdom of God.”

Luke
Chapter 18:1-14

Prayer and the Parable of the Persistent Widow

1 Then Jesus told them a parable to show them they should always pray and not lose heart. 2 He said, “In a certain city there was a judge who neither feared God nor respected people. 3 There was also a widow in that city who kept coming to him and saying, ‘Give me justice against my adversary.’ 4 For a while he refused, but later on he said to himself, ‘Though I neither fear God nor have regard for people, 5 yet because this widow keeps on bothering me, I will give her justice, or in the end she will wear me out by her unending pleas.’” 6 And the Lord said, “Listen to what the unrighteous judge says! 7 Won’t God give justice to his chosen ones, who cry out to him day and night? Will he delay long to help them? 8 I tell you, he will give them justice speedily. Nevertheless, when the Son of Man comes, will he find faith on earth?”

The Parable of the Pharisee and Tax Collector

9 Jesus also told this parable to some who were confident that they were righteous and looked down on everyone else. 10 “Two men went up to the temple to pray, one a Pharisee and the other a tax collector. 11 The Pharisee stood and prayed about himself like this: ‘God, I thank you that I am not like other people: extortionists, unrighteous people, adulterers—or even like this tax collector. 12 I fast twice a week; I give a tenth of everything I get.’ 13 The tax collector, however, stood far off and would not even look up to heaven, but beat his breast and said, ‘God, be merciful to me, sinner that I am!’ 14 I tell you that this man went down to his home justified rather than the Pharisee. For everyone who exalts himself will be humbled, but he who humbles himself will be exalted.”

Matthew
Chapter 8:14-34

Healings at Peter’s House

14 Now when Jesus entered Peter’s house, he saw his mother-in-law lying down, sick with a fever. 15 He touched her hand, and the fever left her. Then she got up and began to serve them. 16 When it was evening, many demon-possessed people were brought to him. He drove out the spirits with a word, and healed all who were sick. 17 In this way what was spoken by the prophet Isaiah was fulfilled:

“He took our weaknesses and carried our diseases.”

Challenging Professed Followers

18 Now when Jesus saw a large crowd around him, he gave orders to go to the other side of the lake. 19 Then an expert in the law came to him and said, “Teacher, I will follow you wherever you go.” 20 Jesus said to him, “Foxes have dens, and the birds in the sky have nests, but the Son of Man has no place to lay his head.” 21 Another of the disciples said to him, “Lord, let me first go and bury my father.” 22 But Jesus said to him, “Follow me, and let the dead bury their own dead.”

Stilling of a Storm

23 As he got into the boat, his disciples followed him. 24 And a great storm developed on the sea so that the waves began to swamp the boat. But he was asleep. 25 So they came and woke him up saying, “Lord, save us! We are about to die!” 26 But he said to them, “Why are you cowardly, you people of little faith?” Then he got up and rebuked the winds and the sea, and it was dead calm. 27 And the men were amazed and said, “What sort of person is this? Even the winds and the sea obey him!”

Healing the Gadarene Demoniacs

28 When he came to the other side, to the region of the Gadarenes, two demon-possessed men coming from the tombs met him. They were extremely violent, so that no one was able to pass by that way. 29 They cried out, “Son of God, leave us alone! Have you come here to torment us before the time?” 30 A large herd of pigs was feeding some distance from them. 31 Then the demons begged him, “If you drive us out, send us into the herd of pigs.” 32 And he said, “Go!” So they came out and went into the pigs, and the herd rushed down the steep slope into the lake and drowned in the water. 33 The herdsmen ran off, went into the town, and told everything that had happened to the demon-possessed men. 34 Then the entire town came out to meet Jesus. And when they saw him, they begged him to leave their region.

Matthew
Chapter 12:1-21

Lord of the Sabbath

1 At that time Jesus went through the grain fields on a Sabbath. His disciples were hungry, and they began to pick heads of wheat and eat them. 2 But when the Pharisees saw this they said to him, “Look, your disciples are doing what is against the law to do on the Sabbath.” 3 He said to them, “Haven’t you read what David did when he and his companions were hungry— 4 how he entered the house of God and ate the sacred bread, which was against the law for him or his companions to eat, but only for the priests? 5 Or have you not read in the law that the priests in the temple desecrate the Sabbath and yet are not guilty? 6 I tell you that something greater than the temple is here. 7 If you had known what this means: ‘I want mercy and not sacrifice,’ you would not have condemned the innocent. 8 For the Son of Man is lord of the Sabbath.”

9 Then Jesus left that place and entered their synagogue. 10 A man was there who had a withered hand. And they asked Jesus, “Is it lawful to heal on the Sabbath?” so that they could accuse him. 11 He said to them, “Would not any one of you, if he had one sheep that fell into a pit on the Sabbath, take hold of it and lift it out? 12 How much more valuable is a person than a sheep! So it is lawful to do good on the Sabbath.” 13 Then he said to the man, “Stretch out your hand.” He stretched it out and it was restored, as healthy as the other. 14 But the Pharisees went out and plotted against him, as to how they could assassinate him.

God’s Special Servant

15 Now when Jesus learned of this, he went away from there. Great crowds followed him, and he healed them all. 16 But he sternly warned them not to make him known. 17 This fulfilled what was spoken by the prophet Isaiah:

18 “Here is my servant whom I have chosen,

the one I love, in whom I take great delight.

I will put my Spirit on him, and he will proclaim justice to the nations.

19 He will not quarrel or cry out,

nor will anyone hear his voice in the streets.

20 He will not break a bruised reed or extinguish a smoldering wick,

until he brings justice to victory.

21 And in his name the Gentiles will hope.”

Psalm 119:1-88

א (Alef)

1 How blessed are those whose actions are blameless,

who obey the law of the Lord.

2 How blessed are those who observe his rules,

and seek him with all their heart,

3 who, moreover, do no wrong,

but follow in his footsteps.

4 You demand that your precepts

be carefully kept.

5 If only I were predisposed

to keep your statutes.

6 Then I would not be ashamed,

if I were focused on all your commands.

7 I will give you sincere thanks,

when I learn your just regulations.

8 I will keep your statutes.

Do not completely abandon me.

ב (Bet)

9 How can a young person maintain a pure life?

By guarding it according to your instructions.

10 With all my heart I seek you.

Do not allow me to stray from your commands.

11 In my heart I store up your words,

so I might not sin against you.

12 You deserve praise, O Lord.

Teach me your statutes.

13 With my lips I proclaim

all the regulations you have revealed.

14 I rejoice in the lifestyle prescribed by your rules

as if they were riches of all kinds.

15 I will meditate on your precepts

and focus on your behavior.

16 I find delight in your statutes;

I do not forget your instructions.

ג (Gimel)

17 Be kind to your servant.

Then I will live and keep your instructions.

18 Open my eyes so I can truly see

the marvelous things in your law.

19 I am a resident foreigner in this land.

Do not hide your commands from me.

20 I desperately long to know

your regulations at all times.

21 You reprimand arrogant people.

Those who stray from your commands are doomed.

22 Spare me shame and humiliation,

for I observe your rules.

23 Though rulers plot and slander me,

your servant meditates on your statutes.

24 Yes, I find delight in your rules;

they give me guidance.

ד (Dalet)

25 I collapse in the dirt.

Revive me with your word.

26 I told you about my ways and you answered me.

Teach me your statutes.

27 Help me to understand what your precepts mean.

Then I can meditate on your marvelous teachings.

28 I collapse from grief.

Sustain me by your word.

29 Remove me from the path of deceit.

Graciously give me your law.

30 I choose the path of faithfulness;

I am committed to your regulations.

31 I hold fast to your rules.

O Lord, do not let me be ashamed.

32 I run along the path of your commands,

for you enable me to do so.

ה (He)

33 Teach me, O Lord, the lifestyle prescribed by your statutes,

so that I might observe it continually.

34 Give me understanding so that I might observe your law,

and keep it with all my heart.

35 Guide me in the path of your commands,

for I delight to walk in it.

36 Give me a desire for your rules,

rather than for wealth gained unjustly.

37 Turn my eyes away from what is worthless.

Revive me with your word.

38 Confirm to your servant your promise,

which you made to the one who honors you.

39 Take away the insults that I dread.

Indeed, your regulations are good.

40 Look, I long for your precepts.

Revive me with your deliverance.

ו (Vav)

41 May I experience your loyal love, O Lord,

and your deliverance, as you promised.

42 Then I will have a reply for the one who insults me,

for I trust in your word.

43 Do not completely deprive me of a truthful testimony,

for I await your justice.

44 Then I will keep your law continually

now and for all time.

45 I will be secure,

for I seek your precepts.

46 I will speak about your regulations before kings

and not be ashamed.

47 I will find delight in your commands,

which I love.

48 I will lift my hands to your commands,

which I love,

and I will meditate on your statutes.

ז (Zayin)

49 Remember your word to your servant,

for you have given me hope.

50 This is what comforts me in my trouble,

for your promise revives me.

51 Arrogant people do nothing but scoff at me.

Yet I do not turn aside from your law.

52 I remember your ancient regulations,

O Lord, and console myself.

53 Rage takes hold of me because of the wicked,

those who reject your law.

54 Your statutes have been my songs

in the house where I live.

55 I remember your name during the night, O Lord,

and I will keep your law.

56 This has been my practice,

for I observe your precepts.

ח (Khet)

57 The Lord is my source of security.

I have determined to follow your instructions.

58 I seek your favor with all my heart.

Have mercy on me as you promised.

59 I consider my actions

and follow your rules.

60 I keep your commands eagerly

and without delay.

61 The ropes of the wicked tighten around me,

but I do not forget your law.

62 In the middle of the night I arise to thank you

for your just regulations.

63 I am a friend to all your loyal followers,

and to those who keep your precepts.

64 O Lord, your loyal love fills the earth.

Teach me your statutes!

ט (Tet)

65 You are good to your servant,

O Lord, just as you promised.

66 Teach me proper discernment and understanding.

For I consider your commands to be reliable.

67 Before I was afflicted I used to stray off,

but now I keep your instructions.

68 You are good and you do good.

Teach me your statutes.

69 Arrogant people smear my reputation with lies,

but I observe your precepts with all my heart.

70 Their hearts are calloused,

but I find delight in your law.

71 It was good for me to suffer,

so that I might learn your statutes.

72 The law you have revealed is more important to me

than thousands of pieces of gold and silver.

י (Yod)

73 Your hands made me and formed me.

Give me understanding so that I might learn your commands.

74 Your loyal followers will be glad when they see me,

for I find hope in your word.

75 I know, Lord, that your regulations are just.

You disciplined me because of your faithful devotion to me.

76 May your loyal love console me,

as you promised your servant.

77 May I experience your compassion, so I might live.

For I find delight in your law.

78 May the arrogant be humiliated, for they have slandered me.

But I meditate on your precepts.

79 May your loyal followers turn to me,

those who know your rules.

80 May I be fully committed to your statutes,

so that I might not be ashamed.

כ (Kaf)

81 I desperately long for your deliverance.

I find hope in your word.

82 My eyes grow tired as I wait for your promise to be fulfilled.

I say, “When will you comfort me?”

83 For I am like a wineskin dried up in smoke.

I do not forget your statutes.

84 How long must your servant endure this?

When will you judge those who pursue me?

85 The arrogant dig pits to trap me,

which violates your law.

86 All your commands are reliable.

I am pursued without reason. Help me!

87 They have almost destroyed me here on the earth,

but I do not reject your precepts.

88 Revive me with your loyal love,

that I might keep the rules you have revealed.

Psalm 119:89-176

ל (Lamed)

89 O Lord, your instructions endure;

they stand secure in heaven.

90 You demonstrate your faithfulness to all generations.

You established the earth and it stood firm.

91 Today they stand firm by your decrees,

for all things are your servants.

92 If I had not found encouragement in your law,

I would have died in my sorrow.

93 I will never forget your precepts,

for by them you have revived me.

94 I belong to you. Deliver me!

For I seek your precepts.

95 The wicked prepare to kill me,

yet I concentrate on your rules.

96 I realize that everything has its limits,

but your commands are beyond full comprehension.

מ (Mem)

97 O how I love your law!

All day long I meditate on it.

98 Your commandments make me wiser than my enemies,

for I am always aware of them.

99 I have more insight than all my teachers,

for I meditate on your rules.

100 I am more discerning than those older than I,

for I observe your precepts.

101 I stay away from every evil path,

so that I might keep your instructions.

102 I do not turn aside from your regulations,

for you teach me.

103 Your words are sweeter

in my mouth than honey!

104 Your precepts give me discernment.

Therefore I hate all deceitful actions.

נ (Nun)

105 Your word is a lamp to walk by,

and a light to illumine my path.

106 I have vowed and solemnly sworn

to keep your just regulations.

107 I am suffering terribly.

O Lord, revive me with your word.

108 O Lord, please accept the freewill offerings of my praise.

Teach me your regulations.

109 My life is in continual danger,

but I do not forget your law.

110 The wicked lay a trap for me,

but I do not wander from your precepts.

111 I claim your rules as my permanent possession,

for they give me joy.

112 I am determined to obey your statutes

at all times, to the very end.

ס (Samek)

113 I hate people with divided loyalties,

but I love your law.

114 You are my hiding place and my shield.

I find hope in your word.

115 Turn away from me, you evil men,

so that I can observe the commands of my God.

116 Sustain me as you promised, so that I will live.

Do not disappoint me.

117 Support me, so that I will be delivered.

Then I will focus on your statutes continually.

118 You despise all who stray from your statutes,

for such people are deceptive and unreliable.

119 You remove all the wicked of the earth like slag.

Therefore I love your rules.

120 My body trembles because I fear you;

I am afraid of your judgments.

ע (Ayin)

121 I do what is fair and right.

Do not abandon me to my oppressors.

122 Guarantee the welfare of your servant.

Do not let the arrogant oppress me.

123 My eyes grow tired as I wait for your deliverance,

for your reliable promise to be fulfilled.

124 Show your servant your loyal love.

Teach me your statutes.

125 I am your servant. Give me insight,

so that I can understand your rules.

126 It is time for the Lord to act—

they break your law.

127 For this reason I love your commands

more than gold, even purest gold.

128 For this reason I carefully follow all your precepts.

I hate all deceitful actions.

פ (Pe)

129 Your rules are marvelous.

Therefore I observe them.

130 Your instructions are a doorway through which light shines.

They give insight to the untrained.

131 I open my mouth and pant,

because I long for your commands.

132 Turn toward me and extend mercy to me,

as you typically do to your loyal followers.

133 Direct my steps by your word.

Do not let any sin dominate me.

134 Deliver me from oppressive men,

so that I can keep your precepts.

135 Smile on your servant.

Teach me your statutes!

136 Tears stream down from my eyes,

because people do not keep your law.

צ (Tsade)

137 You are just, O Lord,

and your judgments are fair.

138 The rules you impose are just,

and absolutely reliable.

139 My zeal consumes me,

for my enemies forget your instructions.

140 Your word is absolutely pure,

and your servant loves it.

141 I am insignificant and despised,

yet I do not forget your precepts.

142 Your justice endures,

and your law is reliable.

143 Distress and hardship confront me,

yet I find delight in your commands.

144 Your rules remain just.

Give me insight so that I can live.

ק (Qof)

145 I cried out with all my heart, “Answer me, O Lord!

I will observe your statutes.”

146 I cried out to you, “Deliver me,

so that I can keep your rules.”

147 I am up before dawn crying for help.

I find hope in your word.

148 My eyes anticipate the nighttime hours,

so that I can meditate on your word.

149 Listen to me because of your loyal love.

O Lord, revive me, as you typically do.

150 Those who are eager to do wrong draw near;

they are far from your law.

151 You are near, O Lord,

and all your commands are reliable.

152 I learned long ago that

you ordained your rules to last.

ר (Resh)

153 See my pain and rescue me.

For I do not forget your law.

154 Fight for me and defend me.

Revive me with your word.

155 The wicked have no chance for deliverance,

for they do not seek your statutes.

156 Your compassion is great, O Lord.

Revive me, as you typically do.

157 The enemies who chase me are numerous.

Yet I do not turn aside from your rules.

158 I take note of the treacherous and despise them,

because they do not keep your instructions.

159 See how I love your precepts.

O Lord, revive me with your loyal love.

160 Your instructions are totally reliable;

all your just regulations endure.

שׂ/שׁ (Sin/Shin)

161 Rulers pursue me for no reason,

yet I am more afraid of disobeying your instructions.

162 I rejoice in your instructions,

like one who finds much plunder.

163 I hate and despise deceit;

I love your law.

164 Seven times a day I praise you

because of your just regulations.

165 Those who love your law are completely secure;

nothing causes them to stumble.

166 I hope for your deliverance, O Lord,

and I obey your commands.

167 I keep your rules;

I love them greatly.

168 I keep your precepts and rules,

for you are aware of everything I do.

ת (Tav)

169 Listen to my cry for help, O Lord.

Give me insight by your word.

170 Listen to my appeal for mercy.

Deliver me, as you promised.

171 May praise flow freely from my lips,

for you teach me your statutes.

172 May my tongue sing about your instructions,

for all your commands are just.

173 May your hand help me,

for I choose to obey your precepts.

174 I long for your deliverance, O Lord;

I find delight in your law.

175 May I live and praise you.

May your regulations help me.

176 I have wandered off like a lost sheep.

Come looking for your servant,

for I do not forget your commands.